# Brendan Houng

#### **Contact Information**

Mobile: 0433 507 750 Web: linkedin, resume, Email: brendan.houng@gmail.com github, google scholar

## **Summary**

Data Scientist at Ambulance Victoria. Engaged in analytic sprints to provide insights to internal customers and executive management, communicating complex concepts through visualisations and statistical analyses. Previously, 12 years of combined experience as an applied economist in public policy research and in competition regulation.

#### **Education**

Ph.D. Economics University of Melbourne (2018) B. Commerce (honours)/B. Software Engineering University of Melbourne (2005)

#### **Thesis**

My thesis asked whether elite high schools, which admit students based on academic performance, improve their students' university entrance results. I estimate the selective school effect for an Australian state using propensity score matching and fuzzy regression discontinuity approaches. Refer to working paper Houng and Ryan (2018), which presents the main chapter of the thesis.

### **Professional Experience**

Oct 2018 - Present Insight Specialist

Ambulance Victoria Doncaster, Melbourne

Jan 2009 - Aug 2018 Senior Research Officer

Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic & Social Research

University of Melbourne

Feb 2006 - July 2008 Graduate/Project Officer

Mergers & Acquisitions Branch

Australian Competition & Consumer Commission

## **Journal Articles**

Renzaho, A., Houng, B., Oldroyd, J., Nicholson, J., D'Esposito, F. and Oldenburg, B., (2014). Stressful Life Events and the Onset of Chronic Diseases among Australian Adults: Findings from a Longitudinal Survey, European Journal of Public Health, 24(1), 57-62.

Renzaho, A., Wooden, M., and Houng, B., (2010). Associations between Body Mass Index and Health Related Quality of Life among Australian Adults. Quality of Life Research 19(4),515-520.

## **Research Reports/Working Papers**

Houng, B. and Ryan, C., (2018). Achievement Gains from Attendance at Selective High Schools, Melbourne Institute Working Paper 08/18.

Houng, B. The Effect of Inferred Changes in Rank on Academic Achievement.

Houng, B. and Justman, M., (2016)\*. Student and Staff Attitudes and School Performance, Melbourne Institute Working Paper 26/16.

Houng, B. and Justman, M., (2014). NAPLAN Scores as Predictors of Access to Higher Education in Victoria, Melbourne Institute Working Paper 22/14.

Houng, B. and Justman, M., (2013). Comparing Least-Squares Value-Added Analysis and Student Percentile Analysis for Evaluating Student Progress and Estimating School Effects, Melbourne Institute Working Paper 07/13.

Buddelmeyer, H., Houng, B., Kalb, G., and Scutella, R., A New Household Expenditure Measure as an alternative to the Henderson Poverty Line. Work commissioned by members of the Risk Managers Round Table, 2011.

Polidano, C. and Vu, H.\*, (2011). To gain, retain and retrain: the role of post-school education for people with a disability, NCVER.

Wilkins, R., Warren, D., Hahn, M., and Houng, B., (2011). Families, Incomes and Jobs: A Statistical Report on Waves 1 to 8 of the HILDA Survey. Report commissioned by the Australian Government Department of Families, Housing, Community Services and Indigenous Affairs, Volume 6.

Kalb, G., Jeon, S., and Houng, B., (2010). The Effects of Childcare on Child Development. Research commissioned by the Department of Education, Employment and Workplace Relations.

Wilkins, R., Hahn, M., and Houng, B., (2009). Families, Incomes and Jobs: A Statistical Report on Waves 1 to 7 of the HILDA Survey. Report commissioned by the Australian Government Department of Families, Housing, Community Services and Indigenous Affairs, Volume 5.

<sup>#</sup> Presented at the Victorian Department of Education and Training. \* data preparation

#### **Conference Presentations**

Econometric Society of Australasia Meeting (ESAM), Auckland University of Technology, Auckland, New Zealand, 1-4 July 2018.

Australian Conference of Economists (ACE), Australian National University, Canberra, Australia, 10-13 July 2018.

The 28th PhD Conference in Economics and Business, University of Queensland, Brisbane, Australia, 11-13 November 2015.

North American Meetings for Regional Science Association International (RSAI), Atlanta, Georgia, USA, 13-16 November 2013.

## Media Coverage

Are selective entry high schools worth it?, Blanche Clark, Herald Sun online, 17 September 2018.

Elite selective high schools deliver only small ATAR gains, Henrietta Cook, The Age, 13 July 2018.

NAPLAN results reliable indicator of VCE results for students, Benjamine Preiss, The Age, 1 November 2014.

Last updated: July 29, 2019 Brendan Houng